A Guide to the Bureau of Social Hygiene records FA060
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Leonard V. Harrison Files, 4
  - Leonard V. Harrison Files - Narcotics, 4_1
    - Clinical Work in Opium Addiction - First Annual Summary (Box 1, Folder 552)
    - Committee on Drug Addiction - Reports, 1921-1928 (Box 1, Folder 553)
    - Committee on Drug Addiction - Survey of Scientific Opinion (Box 1, Folder 554)
    - Committee on Drug Addiction - Appendices (Box 1, Folder 555)
    - Committee on Drug Addiction - Appendices (Box 1, Folder 556)
    - Committee on Drug Addiction - Field Studies (Box 1, Folder 557)
    - Farnham Report (Box 1, Folder 558)
    - League of Nations Advisory Committee on Traffic in Opium and Other Dangerous Drugs (Box 1, Folder 559)
    - Narcotics Laws - Manufacturing Countries (Box 1, Folder 560)
    - Narcotics Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 561)
    - Narcotics Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 562)
    - Narcotics Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 563)
    - Narcotics Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 564)
    - Narcotics Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 565)
    - Narcotics Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 566)
    - Narcotics Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 567)
    - Narcotics Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 568)
  - Leonard V. Harrison Files - European Police Systems, 4_2
    - European Police Authorities, 1913-1914 (Box 3, Folder 569)
    - "European Police Systems", 1913-1933 (Box 3, Folder 570)
    - "European Police Systems", 1913-1933 (Box 3, Folder 571)
    - "European Police Systems", 1913-1933 (Box 3, Folder 572)
    - "European Police Systems", 1913-1933 (Box 3, Folder 573)
    - "European Police Systems", 1913-1933 (Box 3, Folder 574)
    - "European Police Systems" - Draft (Box 3, Folder 575)
    - Austria (Box 3, Folder 576)
      Photographs.
    - Austria (Box 3, Folder 577)
    - Austria (Box 3, Folder 578)
    - Austria (Box 3, Folder 579)
    - Austria - "Offentliche Sicherheit", 1930-1933 (Box 4, Folder 580)
    - Austria - "Offentliche Sicherheit", 1930-1933 (Box 4, Folder 581)
    - Austria - "Offentliche Sicherheit", 1930-1933 (Box 4, Folder 582)
    - Belgium (Box 4, Folder 583)
    - Belgium (Box 4, Folder 584)
    - Belgium (Box 4, Folder 585)
    - Czechoslovakia (Box 4, Folder 586)
    - Denmark (Box 4, Folder 587)
    - Denmark (Box 5, Folder 588)
    - Denmark (Box 5, Folder 589)
    - Denmark (Box 5, Folder 590)
    - England (Box 5, Folder 591)
    - England (Box 5, Folder 592)
    - England (Box 5, Folder 593)
    - England (Box 6, Folder 594)
    - England (Box 6, Folder 595)
    - England (Box 6, Folder 596)
    - Leeds (Box 6, Folder 597)
    - Liverpool (Box 6, Folder 598)
    - London (Box 6, Folder 599)
    - London (Box 7, Folder 600)
    - London (Box 7, Folder 601)
    - London (Box 7, Folder 602)
    - Manchester (Box 7, Folder 603)
    - West Riding (Box 7, Folder 604)
    - Glasgow (Box 7, Folder 605)
    - Edinburgh (Box 7, Folder 606)
    - Edinburgh (Box 7, Folder 607)
    - Finland (Box 8, Folder 608)
    - France (Box 8, Folder 609)
    - France (Box 8, Folder 610)
    - France (Box 8, Folder 611)
    - France (Box 8, Folder 612)
    - France (Box 8, Folder 613)
    - France (Box 8, Folder 614)
    - France (Box 8, Folder 615)
    - Paris (Box 8, Folder 616)
    - Paris (Box 8, Folder 617)
    - Paris (Box 9, Folder 618)
    - Germany (Box 9, Folder 619)
    - Germany (Box 9, Folder 620)
    - Germany (Box 9, Folder 621)
    - Baden (Box 9, Folder 622)
    - Bavaria (Box 9, Folder 623)
    - Berlin (Box 9, Folder 624)
    - Hamburg (Box 10, Folder 625)
    - Prussia (Box 10, Folder 626)
    - Prussia (Box 10, Folder 627)
    - Prussia (Box 10, Folder 628)
    - Saxony (Box 10, Folder 629)
    - Wurtemburg (Box 10, Folder 630)
    - Germany (Box 11, Folder 631)
    - Germany (Box 11, Folder 632)
    - Germany (Box 11, Folder 633)
    - Germany (Box 11, Folder 634)
    - Germany (Box 11, Folder 635)
    - Holland (Box 11, Folder 636)
    - Amsterdam (Box 12, Folder 637)
    - The Hague (Box 12, Folder 638)
    - Rotterdam (Box 12, Folder 639)
    - Hungary (Box 12, Folder 640)
    - Italy (Box 12, Folder 641)
    - Italy (Box 12, Folder 642)
    - Italy (Box 12, Folder 643)
    - Italy (Box 12, Folder 644)
    - Rome (Box 12, Folder 645)
    - Norway (Box 13, Folder 646)
    - Norway (Box 13, Folder 647)
    - Norway (Box 13, Folder 648)
    - Oslo (Box 13, Folder 649)
    - Oslo (Box 13, Folder 650)
    - Sweden (Box 13, Folder 651)
    - Sweden (Box 13, Folder 652)
    - Stockholm (Box 14, Folder 653)
    - Switzerland (Box 14, Folder 654)
    - International (Box 14, Folder 655)
    - Notes (Box 14, Folder 656)
    - Notes (Box 14, Folder 657)
    - Notes on Hue de Grais (Box 14, Folder 658)
    - Notes on Weidlich (Box 14, Folder 659)
  - Leonard V. Harrison Files - Boston-Harvard Survey, 4_3
    - Boston Police Survey, 1929 (Box 15, Folder 660)
    - Boston Police Survey, 1929 (Box 15, Folder 661)
    - Boston Police Survey - First Draft (Box 15, Folder 662)
    - Statistics (Box 15, Folder 663)
    - Appendix (Box 15, Folder 664)
    - Working Papers (Box 15, Folder 665)
    - Working Papers (Box 15, Folder 666)
    - Working Papers (Box 15, Folder 667)
    - Plazinski Notes (Box 15, Folder 668)
    - Plazinski Notes (Box 16, Folder 669)
    - Plazinski Notes (Box 16, Folder 670)
    - Plazinski Notes (Box 16, Folder 671)
    - Plazinski Notes (Box 16, Folder 672)
    - Plazinski Notes (Box 16, Folder 673)
    - Charts, 1932 (Box 16, Folder 674)
    - General Orders, 1930-1932 (Box 16, Folder 675)
    - Police School, 1932-1933 (Box 16, Folder 676)
    - Police School, 1932-1933 (Box 16, Folder 677)
    - Metropolitan Boston (Box 16, Folder 678)
    - Metropolitan Boston (Box 17, Folder 679)
    - Metropolitan Boston (Box 17, Folder 680)
    - Clippings and Pamphlets (Box 17, Folder 681)
    - Harvard Crime Study, 1926-1929 (Box 17, Folder 682)
    - Harvard Crime Study, 1926-1929 (Box 17, Folder 683)
    - Harvard Crime Study, 1926-1929 (Box 17, Folder 684)
    - Harvard Crime Study, 1926-1929 (Box 17, Folder 685)
    - Harvard Crime Study, 1926-1929 (Box 17, Folder 686)
    - Harvard Crime Study, 1926-1929 (Box 17, Folder 687)
    - Harvard Crime Study - Reports, 1929 (Box 18, Folder 688)
    - Harvard Crime Study, 1930-1933 (Box 18, Folder 689)
    - Harvard Crime Study, 1930-1933 (Box 18, Folder 690)
    - Harvard Crime Study, 1930-1933 (Box 18, Folder 691)
    - Harvard Crime Study - Clippings (Box 18, Folder 692)
    - Harvard Crime Study - Criticisms, 1931 (Box 18, Folder 693)
    - Harvard Crime Study - Miscellaneous (Box 18, Folder 694)
    - Garett Case, 1930 (Box 18, Folder 695)
    - Garett Case, 1930 (Box 18, Folder 696)
    - Garett Case, 1930 (Box 18, Folder 697)
    - Garett Case, 1930 (Box 18, Folder 698)
  - Leonard V. Harrison Files - Criminology, 4_4
    - American Journal of Police Science, 1929-1930 (Box 19, Folder 699)
    - Briarcliff Conference, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 700)
      National Conference on Police Statistics.
    - Charlestown State Prison Employment Questionnaire (Box 19, Folder 701)
    - Cleveland Association for Criminal Justice, 1927-1929 (Box 19, Folder 702)
    - Cost of Crime, 1925 (Box 19, Folder 703)
    - "Criminal Justice", 1927 (Box 19, Folder 704)
    - Crime Prevention Data, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 705)
    - Crime Statistics (Box 19, Folder 706)
    - Crime Statistics (Box 19, Folder 707)
    - "The Decrease in the English Prison Population" by E. H. Sutherland (Box 19, Folder 708)
    - Detectives, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 709)
    - Detroit Crime Statistics, 1928 (Box 19, Folder 710)
    - Detroit Police Forms (Box 19, Folder 711)
    - Durant Award, 1928 (Box 19, Folder 712)
    - German Institute of Criminology, 1930-1931 (Box 19, Folder 713)
    - "Identity" by Giuseppi Falco, 1923 (Box 19, Folder 714)
    - Institute of Criminology (Box 20, Folder 715)
    - Institute of Criminology - Scientific Method (Box 20, Folder 716)
    - Institute of Criminology - Clippings and Comments (Box 20, Folder 717)
    - "An Institute of Criminology and of Criminal Justice" by Michael and Adler, 1932 (Box 20, Folder 0717A)
    - International Police Chiefs Emergency Crime Committee, 1933 (Box 20, Folder 718)
    - "A Job Analysis of Several Prisons..." by Max Winsor, 1931 (Box 20, Folder 719)
    - Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial Criminology Report, 1928 (Box 20, Folder 720)
    - Los Angeles Crime Statistics, 1928-1929 (Box 20, Folder 721)
    - Los Angeles Police Forms (Box 20, Folder 722)
    - Matheson Murder - Clippings, 1927 (Box 20, Folder 723)
    - "Measuring Crime vs. Estimating Crime" by Leonard Harrison (Box 20, Folder 724)
    - "Measuring Crime vs. Estimating Crime" by Leonard Harrison (Box 21, Folder 725)
    - Merchant's Association of New York, 1927-1930 (Box 21, Folder 726)
    - Merchant's Association of New York - Miscellaneous (Box 21, Folder 727)
    - National Commission for Law Observance and Enforcement, 1929-1932 (Box 21, Folder 728)
    - "Police Journal", 1928-1929 (Box 21, Folder 729)
    - Police Department - Organization Charts (Box 21, Folder 730)
    - Police Department - Appointments (Box 21, Folder 731)
    - Police Department - Appointments (Box 21, Folder 732)
    - Police Department - Patrol Operations, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 733)
    - Police Department - Education, 1927-1928 (Box 22, Folder 734)
    - Police Department - Forms (Box 22, Folder 735)
    - Police Department - Tests (Box 22, Folder 736)
    - Police Department - Prosecution, 1929 (Box 22, Folder 737)
    - Police Department - Records and Reports (Box 22, Folder 738)
    - Police Department - Recruitment and Training (Box 22, Folder 739)
    - Police Department - Salaries, Ranks and Grades (Box 22, Folder 740)
    - Police Department - Special Services - Flying Squadron (Box 22, Folder 741)
    - Police Department - Special Services - Policewomen (Box 22, Folder 742)
    - Police Department - Special Services - Vice Squad (Box 22, Folder 743)
    - Police Department - Stationhouse Command (Box 22, Folder 744)
    - Policewomen (Box 22, Folder 745)
    - "Policewomen's Handbook" by Eleanor Hutzel, 1932 (Box 23, Folder 746)
    - "Policewomen's Handbook" by Eleanor Hutzel, 1932 (Box 23, Folder 747)
    - "Prison Life in the Soviet Union" by Elias Tobenkin (Box 23, Folder 748)
    - Prison Statistics, 1928-1929 (Box 23, Folder 749)
    - "Resumes of the Wickersham Reports" by Abbott Ingalls, 1931-1932 (Box 23, Folder 750)
    - Shalloo, J. P. - Bibliography (Box 23, Folder 751)
    - Shalloo, J. P. - Bibliography (Box 23, Folder 752)
    - "Undermining Crime" by Leonard Harrison (Box 23, Folder 753)
    - "Undermining Crime" by Leonard Harrison (Box 23, Folder 754)
    - Uniform Crime Reporting, 1927-1932 (Box 24, Folder 755)
    - Uniform Crime Reporting, 1927-1932 (Box 24, Folder 756)
    - Uniform Crime Reporting, 1927-1932 (Box 24, Folder 757)
    - Uniform Crime Reporting, 1927-1932 (Box 24, Folder 758)
    - Uniform Crime Reporting, 1927-1932 (Box 24, Folder 759)
    - Weekly Report Statistics (Box 24, Folder 760)
  - Leonard V. Harrison Files - Miscellaneous, 4_5
    - American Peace Society, 1928-1931 (Box 25, Folder 761)
    - American Peace Society, 1928-1931 (Box 25, Folder 762)
    - City Manager (Box 25, Folder 763)
    - Clippings (Box 25, Folder 764)
    - Fosdick, Raymond, 1928-1931 (Box 25, Folder 765)
    - Fosdick, Raymond, 1928-1931 (Box 25, Folder 766)
    - Harrison, Leonard, 1928-1931 (Box 25, Folder 767)
    - Memos, 1928-1929 (Box 25, Folder 768)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1927-1935 (Box 25, Folder 769)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1927-1935 (Box 25, Folder 770)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1927-1935 (Box 25, Folder 771)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1927-1935 (Box 25, Folder 772)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1927-1935 (Box 25, Folder 773)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1927-1935 (Box 25, Folder 774)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, 1931-1933 (Box 26, Folder 775)
    - New York City Governmental Research Organization, 1929 (Box 26, Folder 776)
    - Woods, Arthur, 1928-1929 (Box 26, Folder 777)
    - "The World" - Final Copy, February 27, 1931 (Box 26, Folder 778)
    - "The World-Telegram" - First Copy, February 27, 1931 (Box 26, Folder 779)
    - Miscellaneous Pamphlets (Box 26, Folder 0779A)
- New York Police Psychopathic Laboratory, 5
  This series contains the remnant files of the New York Police Psychopathic Laboratory, which were used in conjunction with a study on mental disease and crime. They contain material on cases and drafts of several reports.
  - "Abnormals" (Box 1, Folder 780)
  - Adler, Herman (Box 1, Folder 781)
  - American Psychiatric Association, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 782)
  - "Are Criminals Abnormal: A Policeman's Point of View" - Chapter 1, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 783)
  - "Are Criminals Abnormal: A Policeman's Point of View" - Outlines (Box 1, Folder 784)
  - "New York Police Psychopathic Laboratory" by Arthur Woods, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 785)
  - Report - Section 1 (Box 1, Folder 786)
  - Report - Section 2 (Box 1, Folder 787)
  - Report - Section 3 (Box 1, Folder 788)
  - Report - Statistics (Box 1, Folder 789)
  - Report - Draft (Box 1, Folder 790)
  - Report - Draft (Box 1, Folder 791)
  - Report - Miscellaneous Chapters (Box 1, Folder 792)
  - Report - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 1, Folder 793)
  - Australia (Box 2, Folder 794)
  - Baker Cases (Box 2, Folder 795)
  - Baumes Commission, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 796)
  - Feeble Minded and Insane, 1915-1929 (Box 2, Folder 797)
  - Cases (Box 2, Folder 798)
  - Cases (Box 2, Folder 799)
  - Cases (Box 2, Folder 800)
  - Clippings and Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 801)
  - Clippings and Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 802)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1928 (Box 2, Folder 803)
  - Crime Breakdown (Box 2, Folder 804)
  - Darrow, Clarence - Notes (Box 2, Folder 805)
  - Definitions (Box 2, Folder 806)
  - Forms (Box 2, Folder 807)
  - Graphs (Box 2, Folder 808)
  - Interviews (Box 2, Folder 809)
  - Laboratory and Control Cases, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 810)
  - Laboratory Costs (Box 2, Folder 811)
  - Laboratory Reports, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 812)
  - Laboratory Comments (Box 3, Folder 813)
  - Laboratory - Mitigating Factors (Box 3, Folder 814)
  - Laboratory - Cases to Use (Box 3, Folder 815)
  - Notes (Box 3, Folder 816)
  - Notes (Box 3, Folder 817)
  - Overholser, Winfred (Box 3, Folder 818)
  - Procedures (Box 3, Folder 819)
  - Reports, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 820)
  - Reports, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 821)
  - Reports, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 822)
  - District of Columbia (Box 3, Folder 823)
  - Florida (Box 3, Folder 824)
  - Georgia (Box 3, Folder 825)
  - Illinois (Box 3, Folder 826)
  - Indiana (Box 3, Folder 827)
  - Kansas (Box 3, Folder 828)
  - Louisiana (Box 3, Folder 829)
  - Massachusetts (Box 3, Folder 830)
  - Michigan (Box 3, Folder 831)
  - Mississippi (Box 3, Folder 832)
  - Missouri (Box 3, Folder 833)
  - Nebraska (Box 3, Folder 834)
  - New Jersey (Box 3, Folder 835)
  - New York (Box 3, Folder 836)
  - Ohio (Box 3, Folder 837)
  - Oklahoma (Box 3, Folder 838)
  - Oregon (Box 3, Folder 839)
  - Pennsylvania (Box 3, Folder 840)
  - Tennessee (Box 3, Folder 841)
  - Texas (Box 3, Folder 842)
  - Wisconsin (Box 3, Folder 843)
  - Wyoming (Box 3, Folder 844)
  - Thomas, W. I. - Notes (Box 4, Folder 845)
  - Tunney, Thomas, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 846)
  - Winsor, Max, 1926-1928 (Box 4, Folder 847)
  - Woods, Arthur - Notes (Box 4, Folder 848)
  - Woods Survey Summaries (Box 4, Folder 849)
  - Woods Survey Summaries (Box 4, Folder 850)
  - Woods Survey Summaries (Box 4, Folder 851)
  - Woods Survey Summaries (Box 4, Folder 852)
  - Woods Survey Summaries (Box 4, Folder 853)
  - Woods Survey Summaries (Box 4, Folder 854)
  - Woods Survey Summaries (Box 4, Folder 855)
- Bureau of Social Hygiene photographs, 1017
  Biographical / Historical
  The Bureau of Social Hygiene resulted from the appointment of John D. Rockefeller, Jr., to a Special Grand Jury to investigate white slavery in New York City in 1910. In conferences taken in the course of this investigation, Mr. Rockefeller, Jr., became convinced that for a lasting improvement of conditions a permanent organization was needed. On March 22, 1911, The Committee of Three, including Mr. Rockefeller, Jr., Paul Warburg, and Starr Murphy, met. The name "Bureau of Social Hygiene" was first used in October of that year, but not consistently until 1913.
  In 1913 the Bureau was incorporated and its purpose was stated as "...the study, amelioration, and prevention of those social conditions, crimes, and diseases which adversely affect the well being of society, with special reference to prostitution and the evils associated therewith." The Bureau would engage in research and education, publish reports, and employ and/or cooperate with other public or private agencies to obtain these goals. The emphasis in the years from 1911 until the reorganization of 1928 was mainly on prostitution, the control of vice, and, through that, the relationships to police organization. Narcotics was also an early interest. Throughout these early years, Katherine Bement Davis, Commissioner of Charities and Correction of New York and later Superintendent of Bedford Hills Reformatory, guided the Bureau as General Secretary.
  Miss Davis resigned in 1928 and Lawrence B. Dunham was appointed Director. Under Mr. Dunham's administration, from 1928-1934, the Bureau developed a broadened interest in criminology. In 1929 the certificate of incorporation was amended and the emphasis on prostitution was dropped. Criminology embraced crime reporting, police training and education, penology, criminal law, and juvenile delinquency. While studies and projects were still conducted in narcotics and social hygiene, the main thrust of the organization was crime and criminology.
  The Bureau functioned through grants. It was not a foundation and had no set endowment. In the very early years of its existence, financial backing came from several sources including Paul Warburg, the New York Foundation, and John D. Rockefeller, Jr., although throughout the history of the Bureau, Mr. Rockefeller, Jr., was always the main contributor. Grants were occasionally channeled through the Bureau from the Spelman Fund of New York and the Rockefeller Foundation.
  Grants were made by the Bureau for a variety of types of work. Research studies were conducted, such as the Institute of Criminology and the Crew Study; books were published, such as "European Police Systems" and "Policewoman's Handbook"; fellowships were given, as were the fellowships in prison study; and experiments were conducted at the Massachusetts State Prison Colony and the Laboratory of Social Hygiene at Bedford Hills. Grants were most often long range covering periods of from three to five years. Although the Bureau did not interfere in the conduct of a project once money had been granted, it was careful in its selection of projects and kept in close touch during the life of the project.
  The Bureau ceased making new appropriations in 1934 and by mid-1937 all the previous commitments had been brought to a close. Annual meetings were held until 1940 when the Bureau was dissolved on November 13th.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Photographs, slides, and other images are open for scholarly research.
  RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
  Collection is open for scholarly research. Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
  Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
  Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.)
  - Decline of the Prison Population in England (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Prisons, Germany.
  - European Police Systems - France (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Law enforcement, vehicles.
  - European Police Systems (Box 3, Folder 0029A)
    Law enforcement, fingerprints, England, Germany, Austria.
  - Narcotics (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Merck, industry, Germany.
  - New York Police Psychopathic Laboratory (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Insanity, law enforcement.